Kato Drake Smith

iOS & Android Mobile Developer & UI/UX Designer

Nairobi

ryansmith7119@gmail.com

+256 787 667581

Design Oriented iOS & Android developer with over 6 years of iOS mobile development using Swift & SwiftUI for iOS and Java & Kotlin for Android. Deep experience of full development life cycle - from UI/ UX design, to software architecture, through deployment and its consequential updates.

Expert in development methodologies, tools, and processes contributing to the design, deploy, and the incorporation of feedback into iOS & Android mobile applications.

Known for excellent troubleshooting skills - able to analyze code and engineer well-researched, costeffective and responsive solutions.

UX/UI Design: In my previous roles I have been responsible for discovering, defining a problem and designing a solution based on human-centered design where I designed and launched customer feedback systems for software companies, improving net promoter score by 30 points in pilot teams over 6 months.

Led with product and marketing teams to redesign the mobile onboarding process, improving retention and

user experience by 40%

Website: https://drakeson.github.io

SKILLS

Programming Languages: Swift, SwiftUI, Java, Kotlin, RxAndroid, RxSwift, HTML, CSS, Javascript. First Party SDKs: UlKit, Foundation, Map Kit, Auto Layout, Storyboards, Navigation Architecture, Constraint Layouts.

Third Party SDKs / Systems: AFNetwork, RestKit, Fabric.io (Crashlytics), Google Analytics, GraphQL, Microsoft SQL Server, REST API, Retrofit, Alamofire, Firebase, Maps, Media Players, Flutterwave, Stripe, Paypal

Source Control: Git, GitHub, BitBucket, SourceTree

Testing: XCTest, UI Automation, CI/CD experience, UI/Unit testing, AB Testing.

Package Management: Cocoa Pods, Carthage, Git Submodules, SVN Externals, Gradle, Jetpack.

UX/UI Skills: Agile Methodologies, Adobe XD, Figma, In vision, Sketch App, JIRA, Storyboarding, User Stories, User Personas, Journey Maps, Competitive Audit, Storyboards, Information Architecture, User Research, Product Management, Usability Testing, Data Visualization, Experience Design

Willing to relocate: Anywhere

Work Experience

Head Mobile Apps Developer

Code 256 Limited - Kampala, UG

August 2017 to Present

Uganda

Responsibilities:

- Illustrate design ideas using storyboards, process flows and sitemaps
- Identify and troubleshoot UX problems (e.g. responsiveness)
- Conduct layout adjustments based on user feedback
- Discussing the client's requirements and the proposed solution with colleagues.
- Developing application programming interfaces (APIs) to support mobile functionality.
- Keeping up to date with the terminology, concepts and best practices for coding mobile apps.
- Working closely with colleagues to constantly innovate app functionality and design
- Work with various companies to sponsor apps and develop a budget before production increases.
- Present finished project to upper management to receive final approval.
- Android and iOS Accounts

UI/UX Designer

Code 256 Limited - Kampala June 2017 to Present

Munno App (AI based App) Redesign Android & IOS

Munno is a voice application that uses artificial intelligence to provide timely sexual reproductive health solutions to a user. This AI was developed so as to ease the interactions with which a user might find hard to go to a counselor or even go tell his parents.

Design: Adobe XD & Figma

Roles:

- Investigating user experience design requirements for our suite of digital assets.
- Developing and conceptualizing a comprehensive UI/UX design strategy for Munno brand.
- Producing high-quality UX design solutions through wireframes, visual and graphic designs, flow diagrams, storyboards, site maps, and prototypes.
- Designing UI elements and tools such as navigation menus, search boxes, tabs, and widgets for our digital assets.
- Testing UI elements such as CTAs, banners, page layouts, page designs, page flows, and target links for landing pages.
- Collaborating with the marketing team, and internal and external designers to ensure the creation and delivery of tailored experiences for the digital user.
- Providing advice and guidance on the implementation of UX research methodologies and testing activities in order to analyze and predict user behavior.
- Adhering to style standards on typography and graphic design.

UI/UX Designer

Divergent UX Studio - Kampala February 2020 to February 2022

Responsibilities included:

- Gather and evaluate user requirements in collaboration with product managers and engineers
- Independently execute a full UX Design process, from research to production, for new features or feature enhancements

- Develop and execute UX Research Plans for new and prospective features and summarise and interpret research findings
- Prepare and conduct user interviews, user ideations, observed workflows, and user prototype tests
- Continuously improve our visual design work and UX processes using the newest techniques and approaches such as the One Day Design Sprint
- Work in close collaboration with users, Product leadership, Development, Branding, and other key stakeholders
- Create beautiful, polished, production-ready web and mobile designs that adhere to company branding standards and UX best practices
- Illustrate design ideas using storyboards, process flows and sitemaps
- · Creating user-centered designs by understanding business requirements, and user feedback
- Creating user flows, wireframes, prototypes and mockups
- Translating requirements into style guides, design systems, design patterns and attractive user interfaces
- Designing UI elements such as input controls, navigational components and informational components
- Creating original graphic designs (e.g. images, sketches and tables)
- Identifying and troubleshooting UX problems (e.g. responsiveness)
- Actively collaborate with developers during product development and release within an Agile environment
- Incorporating customer feedback, usage metrics, and usability findings into design in order to enhance user experience

Head Mobile Apps Developer

Jamaican Jerky - Kampala July 2021 to December 2021

Responsibilities:

- Develop UI mockups and prototypes that clearly illustrate how apps function and look like.
- Design and develop advanced features for iOS and Android.
- Work with various remote data sources and APIs via REST and JSON.
- Support the entire application lifecycle (concept, design, test, release and support).
- Work on native app bug fixes and performance enhancements.

Head Mobile Apps Developer

Collywood TV - London June 2021 to November 2021

Responsibilities:

- Illustrate design ideas using storyboards, process flows and sitemaps
- Identify and troubleshoot UX problems (e.g. responsiveness)
- Conduct layout adjustments based on user feedback
- Discussing the client's requirements and the proposed solution with colleagues.
- Developing application programming interfaces (APIs) to support mobile functionality.
- Keeping up to date with the terminology, concepts and best practices for coding mobile apps.
- Working closely with colleagues to constantly innovate app functionality and design
- Work with various companies to sponsor apps and develop a budget before production increases.
- Present finished project to upper management to receive final approval.
- Android and iOS Accounts

Mid Level Game Designer

Brayta Innovations Limited - Kampala, UG October 2020 to March 2021

Uganda

Responsibilities:

- Ran trial runs and interviewed test players to determine where games could be improved.
- Reviewed competitive products to ensure the company did not create an exact same game.
- Wrote dialogue for the game with assistance of professional screenwriters.
- Documented every step of the design process to have in the database to call upon later.

Android & iOS Mobile Application Developer

Fortune 500 Klub Limited - Kampala, UG

October 2019 to March 2021

Fortune 500 Klub Limited, Kampala Uganda

Responsibilities:

- Develop UI mockups and prototypes that clearly illustrate how apps function and look like.
- Design and develop advanced features for iOS and Android.
- Work with various remote data sources and APIs via REST and JSON.
- Support the entire application lifecycle (concept, design, test, release and support).
- Work on native app bug fixes and performance enhancements.
- www.fortune500klub.com

Android & iOS Mobile Application Developer

Darlins Limited - Kampala, UG October 2019 to February 2021

Uganda

Responsibilities:

- Support the entire application lifecycle (concept, design, test, release and support).
- Write high quality code following best practices and standards for coding, compliance, security, and performance.
- Develops customer features and key infrastructure components for mobile applications running on Android, iOS, and other platforms.
- Plans tasks with the support of the team and Scrum Master.

Android & iOS Mobile Application Developer

Lyx, LLC - Los Angeles, CA

February 2020 to February 2020

United States (Open Sourced)

Responsibilities:

- Build new features end-to-end through prototyping, validation, implementation, launch, and further iteration.
- Write high quality code following best practices and standards for coding, compliance, security, and performance.
- Develops customer features and key infrastructure components for mobile applications running on Android, iOS, and other platforms.
- Plans tasks with the support of the team and Scrum Master.

UI/UX Designer

Fashlit - Kampala

August 2018 to September 2019

Roles:

- Investigating user experience design requirements for our suite of digital assets.
- Developing and conceptualizing a comprehensive UI/UX design strategy for Munno brand.
- Producing high-quality UX design solutions through wireframes, visual and graphic designs, flow diagrams, storyboards, site maps, and prototypes.
- Designing UI elements and tools such as navigation menus, search boxes, tabs, and widgets for our digital assets.
- Testing UI elements such as CTAs, banners, page layouts, page designs, page flows, and target links for landing pages.
- Collaborating with the marketing team, and internal and external designers to ensure the creation and delivery of tailored experiences for the digital user.
- Providing advice and guidance on the implementation of UX research methodologies and testing activities in order to analyze and predict user behavior.
- Adhering to style standards on typography and graphic design.

Education

Bachelor Degree of Information Technology in Information Technology

Ndejje University

2014 to 2017

Skills

- Adobe XD
- Adobe Illustrator
- Adobe Photoshop
- Adobe Spark Post Design: Sketch App
- Figma
 - Programming: HTML
- CSS
- JS
- PHP
- SOL

Frameworks & Libraries: Firebase

- · Dialog flow
- ARKit
- RX-Swift
- RX-Android
- Bootstrap
- Flutter

- APIs
- Java
- MySQL
- User Interface (UI)
- REST
- Jira
- Application Development
- Agile
- Unit Testing
- User Experience (UX)
- Git
- GitHub
- Test Cases
- SDKs
- Continuous integration
- Android development
- Social media management
- Swift (7 years)
- Android development (7 years)
- iOS development (6 years)
- Java (7 years)
- kotlin (1 year)
- InVision
- B2B
- E-commerce

Links

https://apple.co/2WpVXTQ

https://apps.apple.com/ug/app/collywood/id1577445872

https://apps.apple.com/ug/app/jamaican-jerky/id1591402551

https://apps.apple.com/ug/developer/darlins-limited/id1521883080

https://apps.apple.com/us/developer/fortune-500-klub/id1465395509

https://github.com/drakeson

https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.jamaicanjerky.user&hl=en&gl=US

https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=ug.code.collywood&hl=en&gl=US

 $\underline{https://play.google.com/store/apps/developer?id = Code + 256 + Limited}$

https://play.google.com/store/apps/developer?id=Darlins+Ltd

https://play.google.com/store/apps/developer?id=Paycad+International+Limited

Certifications and Licenses

Google UX Design Professional Certificate

October 2021 to Present

User experience (UX) designers focus on the interaction that users have with products, like websites, apps, and physical objects. They make those everyday interactions useful, enjoyable, and accessible. Over 7 courses, gain in-demand skills that will prepare you for an entry-level job. At under 10 hours per week, you can complete the certificate in less than 6 months.

You will create designs on paper and in digital design tools like Figma and Adobe XD.